## **SOUMOJIT CHOWDHURY**

A Python Developer/ Data Scientist with 5+ years of experience spanning in the areas of Insurance, Retail and Energy Analytics with keen focus on Statistical Modelling, Predictive Analytics, Machine Learning and Data Engineering. Seeking an opportunity to leverage my diverse skills and experience in data analytics/ Python Development.

**Phone**: +91-9874113384

LinkedIn: @soumojit-chowdhury-

08926595

Email:

soumojit.chowdhury@gmail.com

Languages Known: English,

Bengali, Hindi

#### **KEY SKILLS**

## **Python Development**

- Python 2/3, Flask
- ScikitLearn, Numpy, Pandas, Joblib
- TensorFlow, Keras
- PySpark MLLib, Spark Dataframes

# Machine Learning, Deep Learning

- Linear Regression, Logistic Regression
- Exploratory Data Analysis
- Support Vector Machines, Decision Trees, Random Forest, Bagging & Boosting Techniques
- Convolutional Neural Networks, LSTM, Encoders

#### **Data Visualization**

- Microsoft Power BI
- Python Libraries -Matplotlib, Plotly, Seaborn

#### **Databases**

- DB2
- PL/SQL
- MS SQL Server
- NoSQL
- GraphDB
- Azure SQL Databases
- Spark SQL

## Cloud and DevOps

- Bamboo, GIT, Gitlab
- Microsoft Azure

#### **SDLC**

- Agile, BitBucket
- ER Diagrams
- Jira, Scrum
- Waterfall

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Cognizant Technology Solutions**

#### **ASSOCIATE/ DATA SCIENTIST**

August 2018 - Present

Working in the Artificial Intelligence and Analytics team on delivering state of the art Al Solutions to clients across the globe. Currently working for an Insurance client.

## **Duties & Projects:**

- Increased the profit of the client by 6%, by building Predictive models for Lapsed Policy Holders that helped in identifying customers those have high chances of reviving their lapsed policies.
- Clustered and segmented the customers into groups based on different parameters to help the management in decision-making, resulting in 18% increase in user retention.
- Explored several modelling techniques for predicting key outcomes, and showed that important behavior patterns could be predicted accurately at the policy level.
- Strategized and Implemented Premium Predictor which can predict the amount of premium the customer is willing to pay, in order to target customers with specific insurance plans, thus increasing policy sales by 15%.
- Constructed data aggregations using PySpark and Spark SQL in Azure Cloud Services for reporting, dashboarding and ad-hoc analysis.
- Modernized legacy systems to cloud infrastructure (Azure Cloud) through a multiyear roadmap, that also accounts for improved data governance and modernization best practices, with focus on better data visualization using Microsoft Power BI.

#### **Infosys Limited**

#### SENIOR SYSTEMS ENGINEER/ JR. PYTHON DEVELOPER

August 2015 – August 2018

Spearheaded a wide array of different projects and initiatives across different disciplines and industries, including Retail, Supply Chain and Energy Analytics. Drove the development of delivery projects, leveraging on my technical knowledge to guide teams and support the projects' progress.

#### **Duties & Projects:**

- Worked on Fraud Detection and data profiling at distributor/ merchant level using Custom Analysis, Logistic Regression Techniques.
- Enabled optimal Inventory Distribution for retail-based clients.
- Identified improvement areas in customer satisfaction by analyzing survey results done by a third party for an Energy and Utilities Client.
- Built an Energy Planning Suite to forecast the electricity demand for the upper region of Southern California, using which client revenue increased by reducing down time of electricity supply.
- Reverse-Engineering legacy modules related to high-profile application, resulting in uncovering and validation undocumented functional and non-functional requirements.

## **EDUCATION**

- B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering from West Bengal University of Technology (2011-2015) – 76%
- 12<sup>th</sup> (ISC) from Don Bosco School, Liluah (2011) **83%**
- 10<sup>th</sup> (ICSE) from Don Bosco School, Liluah (2009) **89%**
- Certified in Machine Learning (Coursera), Applied Al Course (www.appliedaicourse.com)
- Certified in Microsoft Azure AI-900, DP-900.

## **COMPETENCIES**

- Ability to develop creative solutions for complex problems, Good team worker.
- Volunteering Experience in **Toastmasters International** Served as the Area Director of a region in Odisha, and as the President and PR Manager of the clubs. Appreciated by leaders of the Toastmasters fraternity across eastern India.